Guide to the Andover Newton Oxyrhynchus Papyri Collection
Yale University Divinity School Library
Andover Newton Oxyrhynchus Papyri Collection
0104-0700
RG 305
Yale University Divinity School Library
.5
(1 box)
The collection consists of sixteen Oxyrhynchus Papyri items. The most notable item (Oxy. P. 1230) relates to the New Testament text of Revelations 5,6. Other items include poetical and prose fragments, orders, contracts, receipts, letters, and a prayer.
Biographical / Historical
The Oxyrhynchus Papyri were discovered at an ancient rubbish dump near Oxyrhynchus, Egypt by papyrologists Bernard Pyne Grenfell and Arthur Surridge Hunt in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. The Egypt Exploration Society was responsible for the the distribution of well over two thousand papyri to about a hundred universities, seminaries, colleges, and schools in Great Britain, the United States, and elsewhere between 1900 and 1922. Many individuals contributed to the Egypt Exploration Fund that supported the Grenfell and Hunt excavations and the distribution of the fragments was related to the amount of these contributions as well as other personal connections. It is possible that the papyri in this collection came to Newton Theological Institution in the early 1900s through the connections of Charles Rufus Brown, who was a professor of Hebrew and cognate languages at NTI. In 1910-1911 Brown was resident director of the American School of Oriental Research in Jerusalem.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Andover Newton Theological School in 2017.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of sixteen Oxyrhynchus Papyri items. The most notable papyrus fragment (Oxy. P. 1230) relates to the New Testament text of Revelations 5,6. Other items include poetical and prose fragments, orders, contracts, receipts, letters, and a prayer. The items date from the 1st century to the 6th century. The Oxy. P. 1230 item is Papyrus 24 in the Gregory-Aland numbering system. It is a papyrus manuscript of the Book of Revelation, which contains only Revelation 5:5-8; 6:5-8. The manuscript paleographically has been assigned to the early 4th century.
Manuscripts (Papyri); Andover Newton Theological School
- Papyri, Series I
  - P. Oxy. 861: Poetical fragment, No date (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    B. P. Grenfell and A. S. Hunt, The Oxyrhynchus Papyri VI, (London 1908), 171.
  - P. Oxy. 865: Prose fragment, No date (Box 1, Folder 2)
    B. P. Grenfell and A. S. Hunt, The Oxyrhynchus Papyri VI, (London 1908), 174-175.
  - P. Oxy. 1039: Contract of deposit, 210 CE (Box 1, Folder 3)
    B. P. Grenfell and A. S. Hunt, The Oxyrhynchus Papyri VII, (London 1910), 182-184.
  - P. Oxy. 1055: Order for delivery of wine, 267 CE (Box 1, Folder 4)
    B. P. Grenfell and A. S. Hunt, The Oxyrhynchus Papyri VII, (London 1910), 210.
  - P. Oxy. 1056: Order for delivery of aracus, 360 CE (Box 1, Folder 5)
    B. P. Grenfell and A. S. Hunt, The Oxyrhynchus Papyri VII, (London 1910), 210-211.
  - P. Oxy. 1059: Christian prayer, 5th century CE (Box 1, Folder 6)
    B. P. Grenfell and A. S. Hunt, The Oxyrhynchus Papyri VII, (London 1910), 212-213.
  - P. Oxy. 1072: Letter of Philoxenus, 5th or 6th century CE (Box 1, Folder 7)
    B. P. Grenfell and A. S. Hunt, The Oxyrhynchus Papyri VII, (London 1910), 231.
  - P. Oxy. 1125: Lease of land and loan, 2nd century (Box 1, Folder 8)
    B. P. Grenfell and A. S. Hunt, The Oxyrhynchus Papyri VIII, (London 1911), 218-219.
  - P. Oxy. 1155: Letter to Theonas, 104 CE (Box 1, Folder 9)
    B. P. Grenfell and A. S. Hunt, The Oxyrhynchus Papyri VIII, (London 1911), 257-258.
  - P. Oxy. 1161: Christian letter, 4th century (Box 1, Folder 10)
    B. P. Grenfell and A. S. Hunt, The Oxyrhynchus Papyri VIII, (London 1911), 265-266.
  - P. Oxy. 1179: Apollonius Rhodius ii, early 3d century (Box 1, Folder 11)
    B. P. Grenfell and A. S. Hunt, The Oxyrhynchus Papyri IX, (London 1912), 186.
  - P. Oxy. 1198: Notification of death, 150 CE (Box 1, Folder 12)
    B. P. Grenfell and A. S. Hunt, The Oxyrhynchus Papyri IX, (London 1912), 220-221.
  - P. Oxy. 1230: Revelation 5,6, early 4th century (Box 1, Folder 13)
    B. P. Grenfell and A. S. Hunt, The Oxyrhynchus Papyri X, (London 1914), 18-19. Papyrus 24 in the Gregory-Aland numbering system. The fragment contains only Revelation 5:5-8; 6:5-8.
  - P. Oxy. 1311: Memorandum of a payment or contribution of oil, 5th century (Box 1, Folder 14)
    B. P. Grenfell and A. S. Hunt, The Oxyrhynchus Papyri X, (London 1914), 258.
  - P. Oxy. 1328: Receipt for an unspecified amount paid on account of two months rent [?], late 4th or early 5th century (Box 1, Folder 15)
    B. P. Grenfell and A. S. Hunt, The Oxyrhynchus Papyri X, (London 1914), 260.
  - P. Oxy. 1340: fragment of account; on verso remains of two columns, 1st century (Box 1, Folder 16)
    B. P. Grenfell and A. S. Hunt, The Oxyrhynchus Papyri X, (London 1914), 262.
- Related material, Series II
  - Correspondence, including requests for photographs from researchers, arrangements to send photographs to International Photographic Archive of Papyri, 1937, 1955-1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Descriptions of the papyri, including journal articles in which some are listed, No date (Box 1, Folder 18)